Finding Aid for Frederick K. Sparrow papers, 1925-1977
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Frederick K. Sparrow papers 1925-1977
Sparrow, Frederick K. (Frederick Kroeber), 1903-1977.
1 linear foot
85393 Aa 2
Professor of botany at the University of Michigan. Correspondence and subject files relating to his professional activities, notably his specialization in mycology; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Anna E. Sparrow (donor no. 6917 ) in 1983.
The collection is open to research.
Frederick K. Sparrow, internationally known expert on botany and mycology, was born on May 11, 1903 in Washington, D.C. He attended the University of Michigan as an undergraduate and received his B.S. in 1925. In that same year, he married Anna (Nan) Gabler, a scholar in the field of literature. Sparrow did his graduate work at Harvard University, where he earned his M.A. in 1926 and his Ph. D. in 1929.
From 1929 to 1936 Sparrow held a variety of positions, including instructor at Dartmouth and research fellow at Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute.
In 1936, Sparrow became a member of the faculty of the University of Michigan, where he remained for 37 years. He was considered to be an excellent teacher, and was highly respected for his productive research. He was closely associated with the University's Biological Station and became its director in 1968.
During his career, Dr. Sparrow received numerous awards and honors. From the University of Michigan, he received the Russel Award, the highest award given to faculty, for excellence in teaching and research, and from the Botanical Society of America he received the Award of Merit. He was elected president of several organizations, including the Michigan Academy of Arts, Sciences, and Letters, the Mycological Society of America, and the Second International Mycological Congress.
Sparrow and his wife continued to live in Ann Arbor after his retirement in 1973, and he remained actively involved in research and academic life until his death in 1977.
The Frederick K. Sparrow Collection has been organized alphabetically by topic. Correspondence is filed under the letter "C" and is in chronological order. In the biographical folder, the researcher will find a summary of the disposition of Dr. Sparrow's botanical effects, listings of his personal mycological library and his holdings of rare mycological books and publications, and a detailed bibliography of his works.
Dr. Sparrow corresponded with friends, mentors, and fellow mycologists and botanists from around the world on a variety of topics. His correspondence comprises over one-half of the collection. The researcher should note that letters dealing with the Second International Mycological Congress are included with the rest of the materials from the Congress.
Subjects:
Botany.; Mycology.; Sparrow, Frederick K. (Frederick Kroeber), 1903-1977.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Botany.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Barbering.; Botany.; Cuba.; Douglas Lake (Mich.); Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ferry Field (University of Michigan); Fishing--Michigan.; Gardening.; Hawaii.; International Mycological Congress.; Laboratories.; Sparrow, Nan.; Sparrow, Frederick K. (Frederick Kroeber), 1903-1977.; Sparrow family.; University of Michigan. Biological Station.; University of Michigan--Commencements--1925.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Professional papers
  - Biographical (Box 1)
  - Book Reviews (Box 1)
    (includes one mini-review by Sparrow, all others are reviews of Sparrow works, also contains some correspondence)
  - Correspondence
    - General, Undated and 1925-1977, 12 folders (Box 1)
    - Letters from Europe, 1935 (Box 1)
    - Letters from Cuba, 1949 (Box 1)
    - Weston, William H., 1929-1956 (Box 1)
      (Sparrow's major advisor at Harvard, mostly incoming, see also General Correspondence)
    - Letters received by Mrs. Sparrow re: the death of her husband, 1977-1979 (Box 1)
  - Fest-Schrift (collection of works dedicated to Sparrow) (Box 1)
    (includes volume and additions to the volume)
  - Music and drama reviews written by Sparrow (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets and Periodicals, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (The Michigan Forester; "The Henry Russel Lectureship"; "The University of Michigan Botanical Gardens"; issues contain references to Sparrow)
  - Prepared Papers (Box 1)
  - Retirement (Box 1)
    (mostly correspondence, also contains retirement dinner information)
  - Second International Mycological Congress, 1974-1977
    - General, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (includes undated) (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Biological Station (session booklets) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Professional (Box 1)
    - Family (Box 1)
    - Personal and University of Michigan graduation, June 1925 (Box 1)
    - Douglas Lake (Box 1)
    - Nan Sparrow photographs (Box 1)